James H. Etheridge and family collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Organizations and societies, Series 5
  - American Medical Association Annual Meeting, St. Louis, ephemera, 1886 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Ninth International Medical Congress, Washington, D.C., ephemera, 1887 September (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Congress of American Physicians and Surgeons, Washington, D.C., ephemera, 1888 September (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Obstetrical and gynecological societies ephemera, 1894-1898 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - State and local medical societies ephemera, 1883-1897 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Annual Report, Illinois Training School for Nurses, 1898-1899 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Etheridge was a member of the Advisory Board.
  - Other organizations (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Among the items is an 1895 "Private Report from the Physicians' Business Bureau" that listed local people with poor credit.
- Medical practice, Series 6
  This series contains bound volumes in folders that relate to Etheridge's medical practice. The record of Etheridge's medical practice is incomplete. See also folders in Box 9.
  - Case histories, 1869-1879 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    In this bound volume (33x21 cm), Etheridge wrote a full account of his cases and treatment. The volume begins with a few pages of notes on a course of anatomy and physiology he attended in Ann Arbor, Michigan, in 1866. Some documents are inserted in the volume, including a letter and case history of Mrs. Hubbard sent by Dr. E. L. Homes, March 10, 1880
  - Patient ledger, 1869-1871 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Bound volume (31x14 cm) lists patients by day, with charges and payments. There is an index to names at the beginning of the volume. The book had little information on diagnoses and treatments.
  - Account of travel to London, 1870 November-1870 December (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Bound volume (24x20 cm) with an account of Etheridge's travels in London. Etheridge married Harriet Powers in 1870. He noted that they had spent the months of September through the most of November visiting Paris, Switzerland, Italy, Austria, Bavaria, Wurtemberg, Saxony, Russia, the Rhine and Belgium, and had now (November 26) arrived in London. "Our chief object here is to benefit me, by walking the hospital & gaining all the information I can here elicit professionally. The chief object of this book is [to] note down things of interest..." Most of the remainder of the book contains lists of menus and recipes.
  - St. Vincent Hall prescriptions, 1871-1872 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Possibly St. Vincent Hall was a dispensary. The bound volume in pencil (20x16 cm) gives the date, the name of the patient, and the prescription.
  - Patient ledger, 1887-1891 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Large bound volume (37x23cm) containing an index of names, and a list of patients, dates of visits, amounts billed, and amounts paid.
  - Patient ledger, 1891-1898 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Cash book, 1891 June-1899 February (Box 8, Folder 7)
    This bound volume (22x14 cm.) stamped "Cash" in gold leaf on the front cover, has been organized by month. For each month, Etheridge listed several entries for "Office" followed by the names of various people and amounts of money.
  - Record of patients and operations, 1893 October-1894 December (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Bound pre-printed volume (23x15 cm.) with "Dr. Etheridge" in gold leaf on the cover. There is no indication about the publisher. The open pages have columns for date, name of patient, name of referring] physician, fees, operation, arrival, and remarks. Only a small portion of the volume was used.
  - Cases numbered 2019-2862, 1898-1899 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    The bound volume is a pre-printed case book for diseases of women. It has spaces for name, date, age, whether married, number of children, number of miscarriages, general appearance and condition, family history, symptoms (broken down by type), menstruation,...diagnosis, and treatment. There is no publishing information for this pre-printed book. Etheridge entered an index at the beginning. There is a pasted piece on the cover which says, "Mrs. H. L. Humphrey, Masseuse, 4943 Woodlawn Ave."
- Oversize box: Additional patient records, correspondence, and miscellaneous, Series 7
  - Correspondence of J. H. Etheridge: Notaway Mining Company, Cripple Creek, Colorado, 1898-1899 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Map of a mining site (Box 9, Folder 2)
    May relate to Folder 1.
  - Correspondence of Heman G. Powers: Durands and Powers, Wholesale Grocers, 1855-1873 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - J. H. Etheridge, presentation, "The Benefits of Association " (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Names of patients treated By Dr. Etheridge in St. Joseph's Hospital, since June 1st, 1872" (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Patient receipts, money owed, and paid, 1893-1899 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - J. H. Etheridge, Notes on a case of extra-uterine pregnancy, 1895 April 13 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - J. H. Etheridge, Notes on ovulation (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Flat box: Large photographs, certificates, and diplomas, 1827-1899; Series 8
  - Large photographs, Subseries 1 (Box 10)
    Photograph of "J.H. Etheridge's Clinic," showing J. H. Etheridge operating in an amphitheater full of spectators; photograph of Rush Medical College; photograph of an operation by Etheridge with the team standing around the patient on a gurney, ca. 1895.
  - Francis B. Etheridge, J. H. Etheridge's father, Subseries 2 (Box 10)
    - Membership in the Medical Society of the County of Montgomery, undated
      Society was founded in 1806.
    - License to practice medicine from the "Medical Society of the County of Herkimer and State of New-York", 1827 April 26
    - Doctorate in medicine from the University, City of New York, 1828
      Large vellum diploma.
  - James H. Etheridge, Subseries 3 (Box 10)
    - Certificate for a course in chemistry taken by J. H. Etheridge at the University of Michigan, 1867
    - Medical diploma from Rush Medical College, 1869 February 3
    - Master's in Literary Arts, University of Chicago, 1877?
    - Certificate of original membership in the Chicago Gynaecological Society, 1885 May 29
    - Certificate as a Charter Member of the Chicago Medico-Legal Society, 1888 January 1
    - Resolutions of Illinois Training School for Nurses on the death of James H. Etheridge, 1899 March 7
    - Memorial from the Physicians Club on the death of James H. Etheridge, 1899 March 8